之前我们考查了流，可以用信号处理类似的方式来组织程序
要记住的是，关键在于我们将程序看起来的运算顺序与实际在机器中计算的顺序分离开来
那就意味着，我们着手处理非常长的流，其中的元素只是在需要的时候才生成
这种按需计算的方式是内建在流的数据结构中的
即使这个流非常之长，我们也可以只计算我们需要的
只有当我们要求的时候，新的数据才会生成
例子是什么呢？
真的像我们所说的那样吗？
举个例子，假如我们想要一个流中的第n个元素
这个过程可以计算出来
n代表第n个，s是一个流，剩下的只需要沿着流递归下去
n是0的时候就是终点
否则，就在流的TAIL查找第n-1个元素
看起来是LISP中很普通的编程方式，但是不同之处在于，我们沿着流取值，只有途经的n个元素被计算出来
因为它们被FORCE了
这里有另一个简单的过程，打印一个流
把流中的元素依次打印输出
我们要怎么做呢？
先打印流的head，流的head这时就被计算出来
然后再递归打印流的tail
如果流为空，就返回一个“done”的消息
如果你构造了一个流 这个流非常之长
这时你再来打印这个流 流中的元素会依次的计算并打印出来
并不会一次性的全部计算出来
正因为如此 我们就能处理非常长的流
多长呢？
无穷
我们用电脑来实践一下
在解释器里，我们输入(DEFINE (INTEGERS-FROM N) 定义一个从N开始的整数流
(CONS-STREAM N (INTEGERS-FROM (+ N 1))))
这样就我们要的全部整数
现在我们用这个表示所有的整数
(DEFINE INTEGERS (INTEGERS-FROM 1))
现在执行 (NTH-STREAM 20 INTEGERS) 查看第20个元素
得到21 因为我们以n=0为结束条件
或者我们来点更复杂的
我再来定义一个谓词
(DEFINE (NO-SEVEN X）
它可以检测一个整数，判断是否是7的倍数
(NOT (= (REMAINDER X 7) 0))) X对7的余数不为0
这时用NO-SEVEN这个谓词，过滤全部的整数
这样就得到了所有不是7的倍数的整数
现在我来查看第100个不是7的倍数的整数
或者你也想知道这个流的全部元素
(PRINT-STREAM NS) 来尝试打印这个流 现在输出个不停
无穷的数应该永远打印不完吧
你可能会问了，你写的这个INTEGERS真的是全部的整数吗？
现在我画一个图来表示下这个过程
这是我们刚才对整数的定义，它组合起第一个整数和剩下的整数，现在我们画个图来看看
抽象地来看，我画一个盒子来表示从n开始的所有整数
它接受一个参数n，然后返回一个流，这个流表示从n开始的所有整数
接下来
哦 给盒子写上名字
里面是什么样子
取得参数n之后，将其 +1
然后递归的作为另一个INT-FROM盒子的参数
最后的这个结果和n组合起来，构成了最后外层盒子所返回的流
刚才那个过程画出来就是这样子
很有意思
这种画法是Peter Henderson发明的，就是之前绘图语言的发明者
这种图也被称为Henderson diagram  画这种图需要遵守一定的约定
这些实线代表生成的流，这些虚线则作为盒子的输入初始值
这些有形状的盒子，它们则是取一个初始值输入，然后生成一个流
现在，你可能又要问了
那个INTEGERS的数据结构真的代表着全部的整数吗？
或者它只是经过了你的精心组织，以至于我们总可以在其中找到我们需要的那个整数？
这有点哲学的味道，不是么
一个东西你无论什么时候去看，它都在那里，但是它真的是一直的在那里吗？
有点类似地，就比如你的存款是否一直在银行里一样
好的 我们再来看一个例子
课程的一开始 我们讲了一个亚力山大海伦的计算平方根的算法
现在再来看一个同样来自亚力山大的算法
Eratosthenes发明的计算所有质数的算法
它被称为Eratosthenes筛法
它是这样的，一开始，先列举所有的整数，从2开始
然后取第一个整数，哦，2是一个质数
然后对于除了2以外的所有整数，划掉可以被2整除的数
我把这个划掉，还有这个，这个...
有点费时，因为我要把这一页上能划掉的都划掉
我一个一个地划掉所有被2整除的数
结束之后，回头看看我们还剩下点什么
好的，我们继续，下一个数就是3了
3也是一个质数
然后同样的，在除掉3的剩下的所有数中，划掉所有被3整除的数
划掉9 15 21 27 33等等
一页实在太多了，我先不划完
看看我们还剩下什么
依次地下一个就是5了
同样地，从除5以外剩下的数中，划掉被5整除的数
这样继续开始划
做完这个之后，取一个数，也就是7
同样划掉所有被7整除的数，然后一直这样下去
全部结束的时候，我也就得到了所有的质数
这就是Eratosthenes筛法
我们来看下实际代码
这个过程命名为sieve
我只是用代码表示了我们刚才那样筛选的过程
sieve，以一个流为参数
返回一个新的流，第一个元素就是参数s流的第一个元素
这和我们刚才演示的是相符合的，然后我们从(tail s)中过滤掉所有被(head s)整除的数，再用sieve来筛选，作为结果流的TAIL部分
就这么简单
为了得到所有的质数，我们以从2开始的所有整数作为sieve的参数
我们来实践一下
这是可以运行的
我已经预先输入过了sieve的定义，所以这里我直接输入primes的定义
解释器打印PRIMES
这样就得到了所有的质数，是不是这样呢？
拿个例子来看一下，第20个质数是什么？
打印结果是73
看，我才刚按下回车，结果就输出了，非常快
现在我要求打印所有的质数
解释器就开始打印所有的质数
肯定输出不完的 现在我们把它停掉
现在我用图形来表示这个过程
我已经画好了
这个过程的图形应该是什么样子呢？
就像其它所有的图一样，一开始就是一个盒子，名字是sieve
它是如何运作的呢？
它接收一个流作为输入
head 和 tail 分开
sieve盒子输出的也是一个流，第一个元素就是head
这个head也还用在了filter这里
这里下面，取得tail流
filter盒子过滤掉tail中所有整除head的数
输出的流又作为一个新的sieve盒子的输入，这个sieve输出的流最后和head一起构成了最外层sieve输出的流
你也可以把sieve想像为一个过滤器，不过它是一个无穷递归的过滤器
因为这个sieve盒子内部还有一个sieve，内层的sieve内部肯定还有一个sieve，无穷下去
我们已经开始接触一些不得了的东西了
我们开始把 以信号处理观察现实的视角和lisp计算中的递归结合在一起
你们可以用它来做很多事
好的，有什么问题吗？
没有，那我们休息一下
我们已经了解了许多如何用流进行编程的例子
那些盒子都有一个共同的特征
我们总是递归地一次生成一个元素，再用cons-stream连接起来。因此我们必须一起思考生成流的过程
这里我们用另一种方式来思考流，不是那种需要沿着流一个逐个元素来思考，而是把流作为一个整体
为了把意思表示清楚，我们来看两个过程
第一个过程是 add-streams，两以两个流s1 s2作为参数
然后
生成一个新的流，其元素是两个流相应位置元素的和
如果其中一个流是空的，我们就返回另一个流
否则，我们就构建一个新的流，head元素是两个参数head的和，然后再递归求tail部分
这就是“逐个元素来思考”来表示的整个过程
另一个过程是scale-stream
两个参数，c是一个常数，s是一个流，结果生成的流相当于是将流s整体缩放了c倍
这个过程表述起来很简单，就是用map-stream和这个lambda对流s进行映射
考虑清楚这两个例子的区别，现在我来具体用程序演示“将流作为整体来思考”到底是什么意思
我们来看这个
假设这样
(DEFINE ONES (CONS-STREAM 1 ONES))
这是什么？
这是一个表示无穷个1的流，因为我们看到第一个元素是1
tail部分是ONES，ONES的head也是1，ONES的tail又是ONES，其head又是1，以此类推
这就是无穷个1的流
现在根据ONES，我再给出另一种定义整数的方式
(DEFINE INTEGERS (CONS-STREAM 1 (ADD-STREAM INTEGERS ONES)))
整数的第一个数是1，其余的数则是将整数全部加1
按这种方式，第二个整数就是第一个整数加1
得到第三个整数的过程也和得到第二个整数的过程类似，就是一个不断加1的过程
它居然可以运行，有点匪夷所思，
这样的过程可以正常运行的关键在于延时求值
我们来看这个ONES
这看起来根本不可能，我想知道ONES是什么，你却告诉我说把1和ONES连接在一起就是ONES
它之所以可以运行是因为暗中隐藏的delay
关键是，cons-stream是只是一个缩写
实际是(CONS 1 (DELAY ONES))
再来实际看一下
这里定义ONES
首先我发现ONES是一个CONS
CAR部分是1，CDR部分则是一个计算的约定
不用担心说ONES还没有被定义，你这里怎么可以写一个ONES
将运行整个定义的时候，ONES就被定义了
所以当我再访问到这个部分时，ONES已经被定义过了
这一点非常隐讳
下面整数的定义也是如此
我可以在这里使用INTEGERS也是因为CONS-STREAM的缘故
CONS-STREAM把1和剩下的部分连接起来
所以我根本不用关注INTEGERS有没有定义的问题
这个定义好像还是不那么牢靠的样子，这里我们用图形来表示一下
怎么画呢？
ONES这个流，作为输出进入一个加法器，进行流的加法
输出是INTEGERS
加法器另一个加数则是INTEGERS，返过来构成一个循环
还需要在这里加一个初始值1才算完成
要是在1这里加上一个延时的器件，看起来就完全和信号处理是一回事
当然也得除去ONES这个部分
如果你了解信号处理的话，你会发现这个图很像一个有穷状态的accumulator
我们可以稍加修改，就可以将其变成一个有穷状态的accumulator
把ONES换成一个流，INTEGERS就应该是这个流的积分
还需要修改的一点就是，在S输入加法器之前，先将其乘以dt
剩下的就不用改了
用盒子包裹起来，就是一个积分器
对一个流S进行积分，这里的1可以换成一个积分的初始值
这个看起来就非常像是信号处理了
这里，还有一个程序来表示这个图
对一个流进行积分
接收一个流s，一个初始值和dt，产生一个新的流表示积分
然后呢？
内部定义一个流int，将其命名的原因在于可以回调它构成一个循环
这个int流初始值是initial-value
剩下的则是将s缩放dt倍，和int相加
最后我们返回流int
我们为int命名是为了在int内部可以引用int
我们还可以做的更多
来看这个
斐波那契数
定义FIBS
斐波那契数是什么呢？
从0开始，下一个是1
剩下的就是FIBS和FIBS的tail的和
这样来定义斐波那契数
这是如何运作的呢？
假如开始计算斐波那契数，第一个是0，第二个是1
剩下的是两个流的和，一个流是FIBS本身，另一个是FIBS的tail
现在的定义中，我已经能看到FIBS是以0,1开始 FIBS的tail则应该以1开始
这样，FIBS的第三个数就应该是0+1=1，这里写上1，这是也写上1
知道了这些之后，下一个就是2
这里和那里就写上2
下一个是3
这里就是3，这下面就是5了
非常精妙的定义
用不了一行
我也可以把这个定义写到解释器里，然后要求输出FIBS，斐波那契数就开始刷屏了
到了这里，相信我们对递归又多了一些理解
过程可以递归地定义，类似地数据对象也可以递归地定义
想想也比较合理，因为我们早就了解了过程与数据之间没有明显的界限
具体地来讲，流也是由过程来实现的，只不过出于抽象的原因我们用流的时候并不想象的那么清楚罢了
因此，存在递归的过程，有递归的数据也就不足为怪了
非常和谐
不幸地是，流并非什么问题都能解决
我举个例子
假如我们构建了模拟计算机来求解微分方程，比如 y' = y^2，还需要些初始值
y(0) = 1
dt = .0001
很久之间就有人构建模拟计算机来解决这类问题
原理非常简单
先拿一个积分器
初始值是1
还差一个输入和一个输出，输出的结果就是y
输入的是y的导数，在这是y' = y^2
所以这里使用square进行map，返回去作为这里的输入，这就是用来求解这个微分方程的图
现在我们用代码来表示下这个过程
这个图究竟表示的是什么呢？
y可以这样来定义，就是对dy进行积分，初始值是1，间隔是.0001
接下来
来表示y' = y^2
dy就定义为(MAP SQUARE Y)
这就是使用流对整个图的解释，不幸的是，并不能运行
你可以看到这为什么不行，因为这个定义y的地方，是dy的积分，额，dy是什么
没定义啊
所以我得先定义dy
另一方面，如果先定义了dy，又会发现(MAP SQUARE Y)
y也没有定义
这个不能先写，那个也不能，没法玩儿了
有没有什么解决办法呢？
所幸的是这可以解决
这边，我们可以用ONES来定义ONES是因为CONS-STREAM中ONES可以延时求值
巧妙在什么地方呢？
为什么CONS-STREAM增加了DELAY就变得巧妙了呢？
原因在于CONS-STERAM这样做之后就完全不用关心TAIL的部分了
只用关心我把1和什么东西连接在一起了，而且那个东西以1开始
CONS-STREAM就巧妙在这里
增加了一个DELAY，就可以进行自引用的定义了
INTEGRAL也可以用这种方式来解决
我们回头再看看INTEGRAL的定义
求积分的时候，只需要关心我们从initial-value开始积分，并不需要了解整个流
因为积分结果的第一个元素肯定是initial-value
integral的内部就是cons-stream实现的
我们可以这样定义，甚至不用知道要积分的流是什么，只需要知道初始值是什么就行了
INTEGRAL还可以修改地更为精妙，以一个初始值和一个流进行积分，我甚至不用关心这个流是什么，直到积分的时候再来查看这个流
换句话说，这个INTEGRAL就像CONS-STREAM一样，被积分的流延时求值
我们这样修改
来看这个过程
改动的并不多，只是这里的s变成了delay-s，一个经过DELAY的流
这个INTEGRAL又是怎么运作的呢？
内部还是一个CONS-STREAM，初始值就是initial-value，这里还要记住，delay-s是一个被DELAY过的流
到了实际计算的时候，就用FORCE来查看流的实际内容
第一个元素是initial-value
如果有人想要查看流的实际内容是什么，就对延时对象应用FORCE，这里称其为s，然后做流的加法。整个过程有点像CONS-STREAM的感觉
这个被积分的流是什么我根本不会去深究，直到你需要它的时候我才会去查看这个流
如果这样的话，对于y' = y^2的问题也就解决了，只需要将Y的定义中dt改为(DELAY DY)
Y就是对(DELAY Y)的积分，这样一来就可以了
我输入Y的定义，要求一个什么的积分，具体是什么我也不关心，因为是一个延时对象
这之后，再定义dy
没有问题了，因为y已经被定义了
所以在dy内部引用y并没有问题
一切都正常了
这两个流都有初始值
当用SQUARE进行MAP的时候，查看后继的元素并不会引发什么问题，y和dy都被定义过了
DELAY除了在CONS-STREAM之内还是很有用的不是吗？好的，大家有问题么
没有的话，休息一下吧
在刚才休息的时候，我不知道你们有没有发现什么事不对劲
我们通过流将程序表面表现的时间关系与实际在计算机中运行的时间关系分离开来，可以这样分离的原因在于流中的DELAY。在某些时候，我们为了利用这种优势，需要更多的DELAY
也就是要显式地来使用DELAY
我已经用微分方程示例过了，如果你遇到非常复杂的系统，其中有很多自引用的循环，这时你需要在什么地方用DELAY就非常模糊了
假如你一不小心漏了一个，程序会出错而且你还不知道哪里出了错
我们显式使用DELAY获得的力量不足以克服大型的复杂的系统，因为它们并不能像流一样把DELAY隐藏起来，这非常混乱
有没有什么解决方案呢？
所幸地是 有
我可以改变整个语言，所有过程表现起来就像CONS-STREAM一样，因此每一个过程都对其参数延时求值
什么意思呢？
就是说 你执行一个过程，并不马上对参数求值
相反地，它们只有在需要被求值的时候才会被求值，因此它们可以不被求值的传递至其它过程中，一直这样传递下去
过程传递的只是计算的约定而已
直到最后你需要查看某个值的时候，这才真正的求出这个部分的值
假如我们这样做了，就不需要显式的使用DELAY了，任何东西都有DELAY，它完全内建在语言之中了
换句话说，技术上这是一种正则序求值的语言，和我们一直使用的应用序求值不同
还记得应用序吧
就是你求值一个表达式的时候，每个部分都要预先计算出来
参数具体求值之后，才代换入过程
正则序则不是这样
代换的过程是一样的，不过并不先对参数求值，只是代换入了一个计算的约定
换句话说，这个表达式作为参数，就直接的把这个表达式代换入过程，并不进行求值直到需要求值的时候
这就是所谓的正则序求值语言
为什么不这样做呢？
这样做了之后，我们就获得了延时求值的所有优点
CONS也会是延时求值的，就和CONS-STREAM一样
也不需要流了，因为列表会自动的像流那样，所有的数据对象都会被延时求值
所有的，不是么？
直到需要答案的时候才去实际的求值
也不用担心这些显式的DELAY了
为什么不这样做呢？
首先，已经有人这样做过了
这是一类十分优雅的语言
其中最为人称道的是一门名为Miranda的语言，是肯特大学的David Turner发明的
它就是用这样的原理实现的
正则序求值，列表就像流一样。如果你用Miranda来解决像质数，八皇后这样的问题，写出来的过程看起来就很普通
DELAY已经内建入语言了
但是这样也有不足之处
还记得我们为什么引入流了吗
我们把程序的时间和它实际执行的时间相分离
如果我们在所有地方都引入了DELAY，这也是我们现在正在做的
编程就完全是单纯地描述解决方案的事了
我们完全放弃了对时间的控制，尽管语言变的优雅起来，但是牺牲了太多东西
并且还有一些致命的缺陷
其中之一就是迭代
我们以前写过，迭代的来求阶乘
fact-iter内部定义一个过程iter，它时刻记录着product和counter的状态，就这样迭代的求解
我们说这是一个迭代过程是因为它并没有把状态堆积给解释器
因为状态时刻作为参数传递给了自身
也可以用代换具体的实践来看，这个迭代的过程，并没有状态堆积导致表达式增长的情况
因此这是一个迭代过程
但是现在用正则序的思维来看
这个迭代过程会变成什么样子
如果你用正则序去进行代换，一直代换下去表达式就会变得越来越长
为什么会这样？
因为iter递归的调用自己，把product代换为(* counter product)
在正则序里，这个乘法在这里并没有求值
传递并代换的只是这个乘法计算的约定
然后iter继续代换下去
用这样的计算约定反复的递归代换
代换
如果你实际模拟下这个过程，你会清楚的看到状态的堆积，所有的约定直到最后才被计算
所以正则序不能表达迭代的计算过程
或许这个问题有更深层次的理论上的原因，事实上许多写操作系统的人都很头疼这类问题。比如你用这类语言实现了一个文本编辑器
但是你才用了一会儿，就会发现已经占用了3MB空间，充斥了未被计算的约定，这个应该是被称为拖尾问题，就因为不能表示迭代过程的缘故
一个针对这种语言的研究方向就是如何采用一种编译技术来避免拖尾问题
非常困难
在不能表示迭代之外，正则序求值还有另一个缺点
很遗憾的是，正则序求值与赋值副作用是不相容的
它们在一起效果并不好
你不能对有局部状态的对象同时应用正则序求值来分离时间延时求值
我来举一个非常简单的例子
假设语言是正则序求值
例子是这样的
注意现在是正则序求值
定义x是0
初始化的变量
下面这个过程 id 比较有趣
And what it does, it keeps track of the last time you called it using x.
So the identity of n just returns n, but it sets x to be n.
And now I'll define a little increment function, which is a very little, simple scenario.
Now, imagine I'm interacting with this in the normal-order language, and I type the following.
I say define y to be increment the identity function of 3, so y is going to be 4.
Now, I say what's x?
Well, x should have been the value that was remembered last when I called the identity function.
So you'd expect to say, well, x is 3 at this point, but it's not.
Because when I defined y here, what I really defined y to be increment of a promise to do this thing.
So I didn't look at y, so that identity function didn't get run.
So if I type in this definition and look at x, I'm going to get 0.
Now, if I go look at y and say what's y, say y is 4, looking at y, that very active looking at y caused the identity function to be run.
And now x will get remembered as 3.
So here x will be 0.
Here, x will be 3.
That's a tiny, little, simple scenario, but you can see what kind of a mess that's going to make for debugging interactive programs when you have normal-order evaluation.
It's very confusing.
But it's very confusing for a very deep reason, which is that the whole idea of putting in delays is that you throw away time.
That's why we can have these infinite processes.
Since we've thrown away time, we don't have to wait for them to run, right?
We decouple the order of events in the computer from what we write in our programs. But when we talk about state and set and change, that's exactly what we do want control of.
So it's almost as if there's this fundamental contradiction in what you want.
And that brings us back to these sort of philosophical mutterings about what is it that you're trying to model and how do you look at the world.
Or sometimes this is called the debate over functional programming.
A so-called purely functional language is one that just doesn't have any side effects.
Since you have no side effects, there's no assignment operator, so there are no terrible consequences of it.
You can use a substitution-like thing.
Programs really are like mathematics and not like models in the real world, not like objects in the real world.
There are a lot of wonderful things about functional languages.
Since there's no time, you never have any synchronization problems. And if you want to put something into a parallel algorithm, you can run the pieces of that parallel processing any way you want.
There's just never any synchronization to worry that, and it's a very congenial environment for doing this.
The price is you give up assignment.
So an advocate of a functional language would say, gee, that's just a tiny price to pay.
You probably shouldn't use assignment most of the time anyway.
And if you just give up assignment, you can be in this much, much nicer world than this place with objects.
Well, what's the rejoinder to that?
Remember how we got into this mess.
We started trying to model things that had local state.
So remember Jerry's random number generator.
There was this random number generator that had some little state in it to compute the next random number and the next random number and the next random number.
And we wanted to hide that state away from the Cesaro compute part process, and that's why we needed set.
We wanted to package that stated modularly.
Well, a functional programming person would say, well, you're just all wet.
I mean, you can write a perfectly good modular program.
It's just you're thinking about modularity wrong.
You're hung up in this next random number and the next random number and the next random number.
Why don't you just say let's write a program.
Let's write an enumerator which just generates an infinite stream of random numbers.
We can sort of have that stream all at once, and that's going to be our source of random numbers.
And then if you like, you can put that through some sort of processor, which is-- I don't know-- a Cesaro test, and that can do what it wants.
And what would come out of there would be a stream of successive approximations to pi.
So as we looked further down this stream, we'd tug on this Cesaro thing, and it would pull out more and more random numbers.
And the further and further we look down the stream, the better an approximation we'd get to pi.
And it would do exactly the same as the other computation, except we're thinking about the modularity different.
We're saying imagine we had all those infinite streams of random numbers all at once.
You can see the details of this procedure in the book.
Similarly, there are other things that we tend to get locked into on this one and that one and the next one and the next one, which don't have to be that way.
Like you might think about like a banking system, which is a very simple idea.
Imagine we have a program that sort of represents a bank account.
The bank account might have in it-- if we looked at this in a sort of message-passing view of the world, we'd say a bank account is an object that has some local state in there, which is the balance, say.
And a user using this system comes and sends a transaction request. So the user sends a transaction request, like deposit some money, and the bank account maybe-- let's say the bank account always responds with what the current balance is.
The user says let's deposits some money, and the bank account sends back a message which is the balance.
And the user says deposit some more, and the bank account sends back a message.
And just like the random number generator, you'd say, gee, we would like to use set.
We'd like to have balance be a piece of local state inside this bank account because we want to separate the state of the user from the state of the bank account.
Well, that's the message-processing view.
There's a stream view with that thing, which does the same thing without any set or side effects.
And the idea is again we don't think about anything having local state.
We think about the bank account as something that's going to process a stream of transaction requests.
So think about this bank account not as something that goes message by message, but something that takes in a stream of transaction requests like maybe successive deposit announced.
1, 2, 2, 4, those might be successive amounts to deposit.
And then coming out of it is the successive balances 1, 3, 5, 9.
So we think of the bank account not as something that has state, but something that acts sort of on the infinite stream of requests.
But remember, we've thrown away time.
So what we can do is if the user's here, we can have this infinite stream of requests being generated one at a time coming from the user and this transaction stream coming back on a printer being printed one at a time.
And if we drew a little line here, right there to the user, the user couldn't tell that this system doesn't have state.
It looks just like the other one, but there's no state in there.
And by the way, just to show you, here's an actual implementation of this-- we'll call it make deposit account because you can only deposit.
It takes an initial balance and then a stream of deposits you might make.
And what is it?
Well, it's just cons-stream of the balance onto make a new account stream whose initial balance is the old balance plus the first thing in the deposit stream and make deposit account works on the rest of which is the tail of the deposit stream.
So there's sort of a very typical message-passing, object-oriented thing that's done without side effects at all.
There are very many things you can do this way.
Well, can you do everything without assignment?
Can everybody go over to purely functional languages?
Well, we don't know, but there seem to be places where purely functional programming breaks down.
Where it starts hurting is when you have things like this, but you also mix it up with the other things that we had to worry that, which are objects and sharing and two independent agents being the same.
So under a typical one, suppose you want to extend this bank account.
So here's a bank account.
Bank accounts take in a stream of transaction requests and put out streams of, say, balances or responses to that.
But suppose you want to model the fact that this is a joint bank account between two independent people.
So suppose there are two people, say, Bill and Dave, who have a joint bank account.
How would you model this?
Well, Bill puts out a stream of transaction requests, and Dave puts out a stream of transaction requests, and somehow, they have to merge into this bank account.
So what you might do is write a little stream processing thing called merge, which sort of takes these, merges them together, produces a single stream for the bank account.
Now they're both talking to the same bank account.
That's all great, but how do you write merge?
What's this procedure merge?
You want to do something that's reasonable.
Your first guess might be to say, well, we'll take alternate requests from Bill and Dave. But what happens if suddenly in the middle of this thing, Dave goes away on vacation for two years?
Then Bill's sort of stuck.
So what you want to do is-- well, it's hard to describe.
What you want to do is what people call fair merge.
The idea of fair merge is it sort of should do them alternately, but if there's nothing waiting here, it should take one twice.
Notice I can't even say that without talking about time.
So one of the other active researcher areas in functional languages is inventing little things like fair merge and maybe some others, which will take the places where I used to need side effects and objects and sort of hide them away in some very well-defined modules of the system so that all the problems of assignment don't sort of leak out all over the system but are captured in some fairly well-understood things.
More generally, I think what you're seeing is that we're running across what I think is a very basic problem in computer science, which is how to define languages that somehow can talk about delayed evaluation, but also be able to reflect this view that there are objects in the world.
How do we somehow get both?
And I think that's a very hard problem.
And it may be that it's a very hard problem that has almost nothing to do with computer science, that it really is a problem having to do with two very incompatible ways of looking at the world.
OK, questions?
AUDIENCE: You mentioned earlier that once you introduce assignment, the general rule for using the substitution model is you can't.
Unless you're very careful, you can't.
PROFESSOR: Right.
AUDIENCE: Is there a set of techniques or a set of guidelines for localizing the effects of assignment so that the very careful becomes defined?
PROFESSOR: I don't know.
Let me think.
Well, certainly, there was an assignment inside memo proc, but that was sort of hidden away.
It ended up not making any difference.
Part of the reason for that is once this thing triggered that it had run and gotten an answer, that answer will never change.
So that was sort of a one-time assignment.
So one very general thing you can do is if you only do what's called a one-time assignment and never change anything, then you can do better.
One of the problems in this merge thing, people have-- let me see if this is right.
I think it's true that with fair merge, with just fair merge, you can begin effectively simulating assignment in the rest of the language.
It seems like anything you do to go outside-- I'm not quite sure that's true for fair merge, but it's true of a little bit more general things that people have been doing.
So it might be that any little bit you put in, suddenly if they allow you to build arbitrary stuff, it's almost as bad as having assignment altogether.
But that's an area that people are thinking about now.
AUDIENCE: I guess I don't see the problem here with merge if I call Bill, if Bill is a procedure, then Bill is going to increment the bank account or build the list that 's going to put in the next element.
If I call Dave twice in a row, that will do that.
I'm not sure where fair merge has to be involved.
PROFESSOR: The problem is imagine these really as people.
See, here I have the user who's interacting with this bank account.
Put in a request, get an answer.
AUDIENCE: Right.
PROFESSOR: But if the only way I can process request is to alternate them from two people-- AUDIENCE: Well, why would you alternate them?
PROFESSOR: Why don't I?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
Why do you?
PROFESSOR: Think of them as real people, right?
This guy might go away for a year.
And you're sitting here at the bank account window, and you can't put in two requests because it's waiting for this guy.
AUDIENCE: Why does it have to be waiting for one?
PROFESSOR: Because it's trying to compute a function.
I have to define a function.
Another way to say that is the answer to what comes out of this merge box is not a function of what goes in.
Because, see, what would the function be?
Suppose he puts in 1, 1, 1, 1, and he puts in 2, 2, 2, 2.
What's the answer supposed to be?
It's not good enough to say it's 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2.
AUDIENCE: I understand.
But when Bill puts in 1, 1 goes in.
When Dave puts in 2 twice, 2 goes in twice.
When Bill puts in-- PROFESSOR: Right.
AUDIENCE: Why can't it be hooked to the time of the input-- the actual procedural-- PROFESSOR: Because I don't have time.
See, all I can say is I'm going to define a function.
I don't have time.
There's no concept if it's going to alternate, except if nobody's there, it's going to wait a while for him.
It's just going to say I have the stream of requests, the timeless infinite streams of all the requests that Dave would have made, right?
And the timeless infinite stream of all the requests Bill would have made, and I want to operate on them.
See, that's how this bank account is working.
And the problem is that these poor people who are sitting at the bank account windows have the misfortune to exist in time.
They don't see their infinite stream of all the requests they would have ever made.
They're waiting now, and they want an answer.
So if you're sitting there-- if this is the screen operation on some time-sharing system and it's working functionally, you want an answer then when you talk the character.
You don't want it to have to wait for everybody in the whole system to have typed one character before it can get around to service you.
So that's the problem.
I mean, the fact that people live in time, apparently.
If they didn't, it wouldn't be a problem.
AUDIENCE: I'm afraid I miss the point of having no time in this banking transaction.
Isn't time very important?
For instance, the sequence of events.
If Dave take out $100, then the timing sequence should be important.
How do you treat transactions as streams?
PROFESSOR: Well, that's the thing I'm saying.
This is an example where you can't.
You can't.
The point is what comes out of here is simply not a function of the stream going in here and the stream going in here.
It's a function of the stream going in here and the stream going in here and some kind of information about time, which is precisely what a normal-order language won't let you say.
AUDIENCE: In order to brings this back into a more functional perspective, could we just explicitly time stamp all the inputs from Bill and Dave and define fair merge to just be the sort on those time stamps?
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you can do that.
You can do that sort of thing.
Another thing you could say is imagine that really what this function is, is that it does a read every microsecond, and then if there's none there, that's considered an empty one.
That's about equivalent to what you said.
And yes, you can do that, but that's a clg.
So it's not quite only implementation we're worried about.
We're worried about expressive power in the language, and what we're running across is a real mismatch between what we can say easily and what we'd like to say.
AUDIENCE: It sounds like where we're getting hung up with that is the fact it expects one input from both Bill and Dave at the same time.
PROFESSOR: It's not quite one, but it's anything you define.
So you can say Dave can go twice as often, but if anything you predefine, it's not the right thing.
You can't decide at some particular function of their input requests.
Worse yet, I mean, worse yet, there are things that even merge can't do.
One thing you might want to do that's even more general is suddenly you add somebody else to this bank account system.
You go and you add John to this bank account system.
And now there's yet another stream that's going to come into the picture at some time which we haven't prespecified.
So that's something even fair merge can't do, and they're things called-- I forget-- natagers or something.
That's a generalization of fair merge to allow that.
There's a whole sort of research discipline saying how far can you push this functional perspective by adding more and more mechanism?
And how far does that go before the whole thing breaks down and you might as well been using set anyway.
AUDIENCE: You need to set him up on automatic deposit.
[LAUGHTER]
PROFESSOR: OK, thank you.